So, how do we begin to dismantle rigidity and embrace emotional agility?
As that young schoolgirl, when I leaned into those blank pages, I started to do away with
feelings of what I should be experiencing, and instead started to open my heart to what
I did feel pain and grief and loss and regret.
Research now shows that the radical acceptance of all of our emotions, even the messy difficult
ones, is the cornerstone to resilience, thriving and true authentic happiness.
And emotional agility is more than just an acceptance of emotions.
We also know that accuracy matters.
In my own research, I've found that words are essential.
We often use quick and easy labels to describe our feelings.
I'm stressed as the most common one I hear.
But there's a world of difference between stress and disappointment or stress and that
knowing dread of I'm in the wrong career.
When we label our emotions accurately, we are more able to discern the precise cause
of our feelings.
And what scientists call the readiness potential in our brain is activated, allowing us to
take concrete steps.
But not just any steps, the right steps for us.
Because our emotions are data.
Our emotions contain flashing lights to things that we care about.
We tend not to feel strong emotion, to stuff that doesn't mean anything in our worlds.
If you feel rage when you read the news, that rage is a signpost, perhaps, that you value
equity and fairness.
And an opportunity to take active steps to shape your life in that direction.
When we are open to the difficulty emotions, we are able to generate responses that are
values aligned.
But there's an important caveat.
Our emotions are data, they are not directives.
We can show up turn mind our emotions for their values, without needing to listen to them.
Just like I can show up to my son in his frustration with his baby sister.
But not endorse his idea that he gets to give her away to the first stranger he sees in
a shopping mall.
We own our emotions, they don't own us.
When we internalize the difference between how I feel and all my wisdom and what I do
in a values aligned action, we generate the pathway to our best selves via our emotions.
So what does this look like in practice?
When you feel a strong tough emotion, don't race for the emotional exits.
Learn its contours, show up to the journal of your hearts.
What is the emotion telling you?
And try not to say I am as in I am angry or I am said, when you say I am it makes you
sound as if you are the emotion.
Whereas you are you and the emotion is a data source.
Instead try to notice the feeling for what it is, I'm noticing that I'm feeling said
or I'm noticing that I'm feeling angry.